<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerninge the Spanishe fleete inuadinge Englande in the yeare 1588 and ouerthrowne by Her Ma[ies]ties nauie vnder the conduction of the Right-honorable the Lorde Charles Howarde highe Admirall of Englande: written in Italian by Petruccio Vbaldino cicizen of Florence, and translated for A. Ryther: vnto the w[hi]ch discourse are annexed certaine tables expressinge the seuerall exploites, and conflictes had with the said fleete. These bookes with the tables belonginge to them are to be solde at the shoppe of A. Ryther beinge a little from Leaden hall next to the signe of the Tower.</title>
            <author>Ubaldini, Petruccio, 1524?-1600?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838421</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14164)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1119:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerninge the Spanishe fleete inuadinge Englande in the yeare 1588 and ouerthrowne by Her Ma[ies]ties nauie vnder the conduction of the Right-honorable the Lorde Charles Howarde highe Admirall of Englande: written in Italian by Petruccio Vbaldino cicizen of Florence, and translated for A. Ryther: vnto the w[hi]ch discourse are annexed certaine tables expressinge the seuerall exploites, and conflictes had with the said fleete. These bookes with the tables belonginge to them are to be solde at the shoppe of A. Ryther beinge a little from Leaden hall next to the signe of the Tower.</title>
                  <author>Ubaldini, Petruccio, 1524?-1600?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By A. Hatfield, and are to be sold at the shop of A. Rither, being a little from Leaden hall next to the signe of the Tower,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title page is engraved.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The tables, i.e. engravings, were issued separately as "Expeditionis Hispanorum in Angliam vera descriptio anno Do: MDLXXXVIII" (STC 24481a).</note>
                  <note>The Italian text was evidently unpublished.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Armada, 1588 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>SEMPER EADEM</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:2"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE concerninge the Spaniſhe fleete inuadinge Englande in the yeare 1588 and ouerthrowne by her Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi>: Nauie vnder the conduction of the Right-honorable the Lorde Charles Howarde highe Admirall of Englande: written in Italian by Petruccio Vbaldino citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of Florence, and tranſlated for A Ryther: vnto the w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> diſcourſe are annexed certaine tables expreſsinge the ſeuerall exploites, and conflictes had with the ſaid fleete.</p>
            <p>THESE bookes with the tables belonginge to them are to be ſolde at the ſhoppe of A. Ryther beinge a little from Leaden hall next to the signe of the Tower.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, CHARLES, LORD HOWARD, BARON OF EFFINGHAM, KNIGHT OF THE MOST NOBLE ORDER OF THE GARTER, LORD high Admirall of England, and one of hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt Honorable priuie Councell: A. R. wiſheth long life in perfect health, with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> AM BOLD, RIGHT Honorable, to preſent this booke vnto you &amp; to craue your fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patronage therein, bicauſe there are many reaſons which mooue me ſo to do. Firſt, the ſubiect matter of the booke, which is your ſelfe eſpecially, and the reſt of the leaders, vnder whoſe happie conduction hir Maieſties nauie preuailed againſt the Spaniſh fleete. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:2799:4"/> the time, which I haue ſpent in the grauing of the ſeueral Tables belonging to the booke, whereby the reader ſhall haue not onely the report, but the ſight as it were of what notable thing ſoeuer was performed by your Honor in that high and honorable ſeruice. Thirdly, the booke it ſelfe, which as it hath beene kept backe theſe two yeeres almoſt from our men in an vnknowen toong, ſo (as I geſſe) it had lien hid for euer, had not the good foreſeene giuen iuſt occaſion of the publiſhing thereof. Laſt of all, the time it ſelfe doth mooue to that which I haue done, which being the beginning of the new yeer, calleth for by cuſtome a NEW YEERES GIFT, that is, as I conſtrue it, a ſigne as abilitie permitteth, of that dutiful thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which I acknowledge my ſelfe to owe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Honor. The which my thankfulnes, bicauſe I had none other more conuenient ſigne, I was inforced to ſhew in preſenting you this booke. Forſomuch therefore as it is now come abroad to the view of the world, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated and printed at my coſt, I was mooued by the reaſons aforeſaid, to craue your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors patronage, that thereby I might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:2799:4"/> withſtand, both the malicious toongs of ſuch as carpe, and the manifeſt iniurie of ſuch as are readie vnaduiſedly to counterfet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans worke: The which your Lordſhips fauor obtained (as my hope is) ſhall binde me foreuer to praie for your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors daily increaſe in all good things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your HONORS moſt humble, A. RYTHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2799:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Who list to heare and ſee what God hath donne</l>
               <l>For vs, our realme, and Queene against our foe,</l>
               <l>Our foe the Spaniard proud, let him o'rerun</l>
               <l>This little booke, and he the truth ſhall know:</l>
               <l>The place, the time, the means expreſſed be</l>
               <l>In booke to read, in grauen maps to ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which when you read, and ſee, retaine this thought,</l>
               <l>That howſoe're the meane deſerued well,</l>
               <l>T'was chiefly God against our foe that fought,</l>
               <l>And ſent them quicke through middest of ſea to hell.</l>
               <l>Whether both quicke, and thicke let them go downe,</l>
               <l>That ſeeke to alienate the title of our crowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> could haue wiſhed curteous reader, that this booke with the tables belonging thereto, might haue come to thine hands immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie after the repulſe of the Spaniſh fleete, but ſeeing it could not be ſo, I muſt count it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter late then neuer. Though it come ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what late, I doubt not but it will breed ſome pleaſure, bicauſe the remembrance of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures paſſed are alwaies delightſome. If in the grauen tables there be any thing which doth not pleaſe thee in regard of the worke, I craue pardon for it, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I count my ſelfe as yet but a yoong beginner, do but yet ſtriue to attaine to that excellencie, which I wiſh for. In the booke it ſelfe the truth of euery thing is ſet downe ſo neare as might be, and therefore it is ſo much the more to be regarded, being alſo by my friend tranſlated faithfully, onely the Italian flouriſhes were here and there omitted, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in our Engliſh toong they could not ſound well without ſuſpicion of flatterie. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine A. Ryther.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2799:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE CONCERNING THE SPANISH FLEETE, INVADING ENGLAND IN THE YEERE 1588. ouerthrowen by hir Maieſties nauie, vnder the conduction of the Right honorable the L. CHARLES HOWARD being high <hi>Admirall of England, written in</hi> Italian by Petruccio Vbaldino <hi>citizen of Florence.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Quéenes Maieſtie hauing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe waies vnderſtood the great and diligent preparation of the king of Spaine, in diuerſe parts both by land and ſea, not only of the ſtrongeſt ſhips of all places within his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: but alſo of all ſorts of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and munition neceſſarie for a mightie fléete, which was to come from Spaine and Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall (for the furniſhing and better direction wherof he had drawen together into the places aforeſaid, the moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and ancient captaines and ſoldiers, aſwell of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Naples and Sicilie, as of Lombardie and other parts of Italie, and the more remote parts of India, as by euery one was long before verie euidently perceiued, by reaſon that the preparation of theſe things togither with the number of the ſhips, mariners and ſoldiors, the diuerſe ſorts and quantities of victuall, the great number and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers kinds of artillery, with the ſum of euery ſeueral kind, were ſufficiently ſpecified vnto all countries by certaine Pamphlets, laieng foorth at large his whole intent: the which Pamphlets were printed and publiſhed in Spaine and Portugall, and other prouinces of Chriſtendome, with this title; <hi>The moſt puiſſant and moſt happie fleete of the king of Spayne, againſt the Realme of England:</hi>) Her maieſtie, I ſay, hauing in this maner receiued ſo open and manifeſt information hereof, as alſo certaine intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2799:6"/> of horſemen and footemen ſent in ſo great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that they were ſufficient for the furniſhing of diuerſe camps in the lowe Countries, vnder the gouernment of the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> his lieutenant generall for thoſe prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; withall knowing the multitude of the ſhips of war, and the poſſibilitie that the ſaid king had to tranſport his ſoldiers out off Flaunders, and land them in England, not ſparing to giue out therevpon open and frée report, that all that prouiſion was for the inuaſion and conqueſt of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: And forſomuch alſo as at the ſame time the king him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by means of his aforeſaid Generall the duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> pretended a certaine treatie of peace to be made with her Maieſtie (albeit this offer was in truth knowne in England, not to haue béene made but onely to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of the time, and to make her Maieſty negligent in preparing for her defence, although ſhe notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous openly to declare her good inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto that, which is a iuſt &amp; chriſtian commendation in a prudent Princeſſe) refuſed not in any point this treatie &amp; offer of peace, greatly deſired of all chriſtian people: and therfore for that purpoſe gaue commandement to certaine noble men of her priuie Counſell &amp; others, with certain Gouernors of her forces in Flaunders, to deale in this matter with the commiſſioners that ſhould be there appointed in the name and behalfe of the ſaid king: And our commiſſioners after their departure and manifeſt declaration that they began to parle to ſome purpoſe concerning this treatie, being driuen off a long time to ſmall effect, and without any manifeſt hope of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréement likely to enſue, vntill ſuch time as the Spaniſh fléete was not onely diſcouered in the Engliſh chanell, but alſo withheld and brideled from their purpoſe in ioyning with the forces of the duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and tranſporting an armie into England: and finallie vntill ſuch time as it was inforced to withdraw it ſelfe and ſéeke ſome better fortune in the northren ſeas, being euery where elſe vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make anie forceable reſiſtance: Therefore her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2799:6"/> as well to declare her propenſe readines, if on their part any ſincere intent of peace had béene, as her vigilant prouidence not to be deluded by ſo ſubtile and malicious an enemie, furniſhed her ſelfe by ſea with a mightie fléete, and by land with no leſſe diligence to reſiſt ſo great forces as by all nations were reported to come againſt her: For it was neuer knowne in the memorie of man, that ſo great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was euer heretofore at one time made out, either by king <hi>Phillip</hi> himſelfe, or yet by the emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>5.</hi> his father, although his power were much more and his occaſions of warre far greater.</p>
            <p>The diligence therefore of the Engliſhmen, anſwerable vnto the care of the Prince, was ſuch and ſo great, that her Maieſtie was prouided of a mightie fléete to defend her by ſea from the enimie, betwéene the firſt of Nouember <hi>1587.</hi> and the <hi>20.</hi> of December next enſuing, a time in truth very ſhort for ſuch a prouiſion, in regard of ſo many yéeres ſpent by the ſaid king in preparing of his fléete, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding did ſhew of what force it was by experience after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards made thereof againſt the Engliſh nauie, gathered togither within <hi>50.</hi> daies, and prouided and moſt excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie furniſhed of all things neceſſarie for ſuch a purpoſe. The care &amp; charge of this nauie was commended vnto the right honorable <hi>Charles</hi> L. <hi>Howard,</hi> Baron of Effingham, L. High Admiral of England, who for his place &amp; office, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courage, experience in martial affaires, and nobilitie of blood and deſcent, was thought moſt fit &amp; woorthy to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied in that ſeruice. He had in his companie a ſufficient number of honorable, worſhipful, and valiant perſonages, famous both in reſpect of their birth &amp; the gifts of mind, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſerue their Prince and Countrie in ſuch a cauſe as this, being iudged of the whole Engliſh nation both iuſt and neceſſarie: likewiſe of ſea-faring men and priuate ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diors ſo competent a number, as might be anſwerable vnto the power of ſo great a Prince in ſo weightie a cauſe. The L. High Admirall therefore with theſe forces kéeping for a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2799:7"/> ſeaſon the narrow ſeas and chanell betwéene England and Flaunders, ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> knight, mentioned here alſo in honor of his good deſerts, was by the aduice of the Lords of the counſel &amp; his honor ſo commanding it, ſent towards the weſt parts with certaine of the Quéenes ſhips and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from certaine ports of England thereabout, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in al not aboue the number of <hi>50.</hi> ſaile of all ſorts, there to attend the L. high Admirall his comming with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forces, if occaſion ſhould ſo require. In the meane ſeaſon the L. Admirall with his Vice admirall the L. <hi>Henrie Sey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> kept the narrow ſeas, accompanied with <hi>20.</hi> ſhips more, verie well furniſhed at the charges of the citizens of London, beſides manie other from diuerſe parts on that ſide of the Realme, that lieth from the towne of Douer vp to the northward, which met all togither in good order, and well appointed for the warres.</p>
            <p>And here the Lord Admirall vnderſtanding for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, that the fléete of the enemie was alreadie lanched and at the ſea, he weighed ancre, and leauing the L. <hi>Seymer</hi> with ſufficient forces of the Quéenes ſhips and other veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to watch what the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> would do, or was able to vndertake by ſea, and parting from thence the <hi>21.</hi> of Maie <hi>1588.</hi> to the weſtward with her Maieſties nauie, and <hi>20.</hi> ſhips of London, with ſome others, he arriued at Plymouth the <hi>23.</hi> of the ſame Moneth: where ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> with <hi>50.</hi> ſaile which he had vnder his charge, met with the L. Admirall in very good order. And then the two nauies being ioyned togither into one, the L. Admirall made ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> his Viceadmirall.</p>
            <p>Arriuing then at Plymouth, his Lordſhip preſently gaue order for prouiſion of victuall for the whole nauie, that it might want nothing, that ſhould tend to the neceſſarie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice enſuing. The whole nauie was at this preſent about <hi>90.</hi> ſaile of all ſorts.</p>
            <p>This prouiſion being complet, he reſolued with himſelfe to put foorth to the ſea againe about the <hi>30.</hi> of Maie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2799:7"/> But the winde not ſeruing his turne, he kept himſelfe abroad, ſailing vp and downe within the Sléeue betwene Vſhant and Sillie, attending ſome ſight or report of the enemies fléete. Where hauing waited a certain time, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles drawing neare to the coaſt of France, &amp; ſomtimes to the coaſt of England, he returned, being thereto inforced by a great tempeſt, with his whole nauie into the Port of Plymouth the <hi>6.</hi> of Iune to refreſh his companie there.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon there were diſcouered betwéene Vſhant and Sillie certaine ſhips of the Spaniſh fléete, not aboue the number of <hi>14.</hi> which were knowen to be ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the whole fléete by violence of the aforeſaid tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt. But before they could be encountred withall by any of the Engliſh nauie, the wind came about, whereby they had opportunitie to returne backe againe, ſauing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from all perils in their hauen called the Groine, into the which alſo the reſt of the Spaniſh fléete was put to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide themſelues anew of other things which they wanted, and ſpecially of freſh water. Of this thing the L. Admirall had intelligence and aduertiſement from ſundry parts, as alſo that the Spaniſh fléete was by great fortune diſperſed &amp; ſeuered into diuers places, through penurie of many and thoſe neceſſarie things, through diſeaſes and mortalitie of men, although the report hereof could not afterwards be verified, whereof the certain truth was, that being troubled with tempeſt, they were commanded to come a ſhoare at the Groyne.</p>
            <p>The L. Admirall therefore ſéeing the coaſt of England and France cléere and frée from all danger, as by diligent ſearch it was vnderſtood, reſolued by the aduiſe and opinion of his counſell, to take the aduantage of the next wind that ſhould blow from the North, that paſſing to the coaſt of Spaine he might finde the enemies fléet ſo diſperſed in the Groine, and in other parts of Galitia where they had driuen by the ſtorme.</p>
            <p>This was put in execution betwéene the <hi>8.</hi> and <hi>10.</hi> of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2799:8"/> the ſame moneth, the wind being then at the North, which within a while changing vnto the South, after that he was come within <hi>40.</hi> leagues or there about of the coaſt of Spaine, made him to caſt a doubt of that which afterwards hapned indéed. For laying this before him as his principall care, according to the charge laid vpon him by her Maieſty, to be diligent and carefull for the defence of the coaſt of England, and conſidering that with the wind which was now changed and very good to make for England, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my might ſet out and paſſe for England without diſcouery of his fléete, he returned back with the whole nauy, and the <hi>12.</hi> of the ſame moneth he arriued at Plymouth, there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to prouide himſelfe of all that was neceſſarie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>19.</hi> of Iune his honor had intelligence by a barke or pinnis, whoſe captaine was <hi>Thomas Fleming,</hi> amongſt other behinde him in the Sléeue for diſcouerie, that the Spaniſh fléete was diſcouered neare vnto the Lyzarde,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 1. table.</note> the wind being then South and by Weſt. And therefore albeit that by reaſon of the great number of Engliſh ſhips which were in Plimouth, it was with that winde very hard to bring them foorth from thence (as the militarie art of the Sea and the condition of their affaires required) yet was there ſuch diligence vſed by the L. Admirall and the reſt by his example, as they indeuored therin with ſuch aduiſe and earneſtnes, that many of the ſhips at the length warped out of the hauen,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 2. table.</note> as if the winde had béen wholy fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto them: which thing could not haue fallen out but through the long and certaine ſkill which the Engliſh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters generally haue in marine diſcipline. To the which reaſon this may be added, that they were all of one nation, of one toong, and touched with a greiuous and equal hatred toward their enemies, being mightily perſwaded of their forces. Whereupon we may in ſuch caſes aſſure our ſelues of what importance it is in ſeafaring matters, for a fléete of any prince whatſoeuer, inuading any forraine ſtate or kingdome, to encounter with a fléete ready for defenſe in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2799:8"/> ſuch maner as the Engliſh nauie was, for ſo much as the fléete inuading being prouided diuerſly of Maſters and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers differing one from another in cuſtome, language, and conceit, cannot in any meaſure giue any aſſured hope of certain victorie, how honorable ſoeuer the commander be. Many of the ſhips therefore came foorth, by reaſon that the men were mooued in the foreſaid reſpects to labor diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo much the rather, by how much the captaines and chéefe officers both by counſel and hand, ſhewed themſelues more diligent and induſtrious.</p>
            <p>By theſe meanes the <hi>20.</hi> day of Iune the L. Admirall accompanied with <hi>54.</hi> ſhips, came foorth with the ſame winde that the enemie had from the ſouthweſt: Which thing certainly was not eſtéemed a ſmall thing to be done, in regarde aſwell of the winde as of the narrownes of the place it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Spaniſh fléete being manifeſtly diſcouered about <hi>140.</hi> miles from Edeſtone, and cléerely ſéene of euery one toward the weſt, and ſo far off from Foye as the Engliſh fléete was, that is <hi>25.</hi> ordinarie Engliſh miles: the next morning being the <hi>21.</hi> of Iune, all the ſhips which were now come out of the hauen, had gotten the winde of the Spaniards, and approching ſomewhat nearer, found that their fléete was placed in battell araie, after the maner of a Moone creſſant, being readie with her horns &amp; hir inward circumference to receiue either all, or ſo manie of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh nauie, as ſhould giue her the aſſault, her hornes being extended in widenes about the diſtance of <hi>8.</hi> miles, if the information giuen haue not deceiued my pen. The reaſon of their arraunging in this order, aroſe vpon the foreſight of the duke of <hi>Medina Sidonia</hi> general of the Spaniſh fléet, who approching the coaſt, ſent out a ſmal ſhip to eſpy ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what concerning the Engliſh fléete, and hearing by certain fiſhermen taken priſoners, that our fléet was in Plymouth, he prepared himſelfe as aforeſaid, for the auoiding of all ſuch chances as might after befall. Whereupon about <hi>9.</hi> of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2799:9"/> the clocke before noone the L. Admirall commanded his Pinneſſe called the Diſdaine, to giue the defiance vnto the duke of Medina: after which he himſelfe in the Quéenes ſhip called the Arcke went foremoſt,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 2. table.</note> as was conuenient, and began hotlie to fight with a great ſhip which was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of the Spaniſh fléete, in which ſhip he thought by reaſon of certaine likely coniectures the duke of Medina to be, conſidering alſo the ſaid ſhip was ſo well accompanied by others. The fight with hir continued ſo long and ſo hot, that diuers other ſhips, yea the moſt part of the Spaniſh fléete came to her ſuccour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As appeereth in the 3. table.</note>In the mean ſeaſon the Viceadmirall ſir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> with maſter <hi>Iohn Hawkins,</hi> and maſter <hi>Martin Frobiſher</hi> fought with a Galeon of Portugall, wherein they thought <hi>Don Martin de Ricaldes</hi> the Viceadmirall to be.</p>
            <p>This fight was ſo well maintained for the time it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, that the enemie was enforced to leaue his place, and to giue waie gathering toward the Eaſt. In the which point of remouing,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 3. table.</note> a great Galeon wherein <hi>Don Pedro de Valdes</hi> went as captaine, falling foule with another ſhip of their fléete was depriued of hir foremaſt, ſo that ſhe could not follow the bodie of the fléete that forſooke her, to the great maruel of the Engliſh men themſelues, whereby <hi>Don Pedro</hi> became priſoner, as afterward ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As appeereth in the 4. table.</note>Furthermore alſo there was at this time a great ſhip of Biſcaie about <hi>800.</hi> tunne in burthen, that was ſpoiled by fire vpon this occaſion: The captaine of the ſoldiors that went in her hauing ſmall regard (as is reported) of an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and ciuill life, did inſolently beat a certaine Flemiſh gunner: what cauſe he had I know not, whether vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of words touching his charge, or by meanes of the gunners wife, whom he had abuſed according to the cuſtom of that nation. Whereupon the perplexed man ſéeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe among ſuch a kind of people, as not onely made him ſerue their turnes at their owne pleaſure, but diſgraced
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2799:9"/> him in as vile maner as if he were a ſlaue, deſpairing both of life, wife, and his yoong daughter, and perchance rather mooued with the diſhonor of them then by his owne miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, (which minde is many times in men euen of meane condition) he ſet himſelfe on fire in a barrell of gunpowder, procuring therby through the loſſe of his owne life, and the extréeme hazard of thoſe that belonged vnto him, &amp; the loſſe of many mens liues beſides, a cruell reuenge of his iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries receiued by one onely man. This example may ſerue to inſtruct ſuch as command ouer others, how they ought to behaue themſelues with leſſe inſolencie: inaſmuch as the minde of man is alwaies readie to reuenge, after the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of this our bloodie age, if he be not borne vtterly void of a quicke wit and liuely ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Through this miſchance of theirs all the vpper decks were blowen vp, all hir furniture marred, and much other ſpoile done, beſides the death and maiming of her men, ſo that being vtterly vnable all that night to helpe her ſelfe, ſhe was ſuccored by the galliaſſes, and for the time ſaued in the bodie of their fléete.</p>
            <p>But to returne vnto our purpoſe. This firſt ſkirmiſh continued not aboue two houres, bicauſe the L. Admirall conſidering that he wanted as yet <hi>40.</hi> ſhips which could not ſo readily come foorth of the hauen, thought he ſhould do better ſeruice if he ſtaied their comming before he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded any further, beating behinde vpon the enimie, leaſt he ſhould bring the reſt too much in hazard, and therfore he thought it not profitable too much to embolden and pricke thoſe forward that he had with him in a matter that was not greatly conuenient, either for the honor of the Realme, or his owne perſon, neither did the militarie diſcipline of the Engliſh nation purchaſed by long experience at the ſea giue him leaue to do it. And therefore he put foorth his flagge to call the other captaines to counſell, who agréeing vnto his determination, receiued inſtructions concerning the order that they were to kéepe in following the Spaniſh
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2799:10"/> fléete. Then hauing giuen libertie to euery man to returne to their charge, he gaue order likewiſe to his Viceadmirall ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> to appoint the watch for that night, and to beare out the light.</p>
            <p>The ſame night the Spaniſh fléete lay about <hi>14.</hi> miles off from the Stert. The next day following early in the morning it was vnder the winde not ſo far off as Berie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As appeereth in the 4. table.</note>In the mean time the Engliſh fléete wanting light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Viceadmiral ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> leauing his place to follow <hi>5.</hi> Hulkes which were diſcouered in the euening very late, it came to paſſe that all the other ſhips ſtaied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, not knowing that they were to follow, or whither to direct themſelues: ſo that there might haue followed ſome great inconuenience had they had to do with an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie more practized in our ſeas. But as it ſéemed by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, the ſaid Viceadmiral was moued to do this by means of a certaine curious diligence and a militarie ſuſpicion, growing in his mind vpon certaine and very probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures, grounded on circumſtances of matter conſidered in his mind: and therefore he gaue them the chaſe, thinking that they had béen enemies.</p>
            <p>But being ouertaken and their officers examined, and being knowen to be friends, or at the leaſt wiſe not ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, he permitted them to go their way, returning him ſelfe vnto the fléete the day following.</p>
            <p>The L. Admirall notwithſtanding accompanied with the Beare and the Marie Roſe comming a little behind his ſterne,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 4. table.</note> by reaſon of the cléerenes of the aire (which at that time of the yéere is ordinarilie very great through out all England) followed the enemy all that night within a Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerin ſhot. By occaſion whereof the reſt of the fléete was caſt ſo far behind, that the morning after the neareſt part thereof could hardly deſcrie the tops of the other ſhips,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 5. table.</note> and many of them were cleane out of ſight, ſo that with all the force of their ſailes they could hardly come all together the whole day following vntill the euening.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2799:10"/>
            <p>The next day the Viceadmirall ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Quéenes ſhip called the Reuenge, hauing alſo the Roebucke and a Pinneſſe or two in his company, tooke <hi>Don Pedro de Valdes,</hi> who as was ſaid before, had loſt the foremaſt of his ſhip: and hauing receiued the ſaid <hi>Valdes</hi> as his priſoner, and certaine other gentlemen of moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that were therein, he ſent the ſhip togither with the priſoners vnto Dartmouth, vnder the conduct of the Roe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucke, and he himſelfe made toward the L. Admirall, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe lée he came that night.</p>
            <p>The ſame daie being the <hi>22.</hi> of the moneth, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Viceadmirall ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> was returned vnto the fléete, the Spaniards forſooke the ſhip which the day before was ſpoyled by fire. To the which ſhip the L. Admirall ſent the L. <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> and with him M. <hi>Iohn Hawkins,</hi> who being in the cockboate of the Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie went a boord her, and there found a lamentable ſight. For all the vppermoſt decks of her being torne and ſpoyled by the fire, there were in her <hi>50.</hi> men miſerablie burnt with the powder. The ſtinke in her was ſo great, and the ſhip it ſelfe ſo filthie, that the L. <hi>Howard</hi> departed preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from her: and returning with M. <hi>Iohn Hawkins</hi> to the L. Admirall, they informed him of that they found and ſaw there. For which cauſe there was preſently comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement giuen, that the little pinneſſe of captaine <hi>Fleming</hi> ſhould conduct her vnto ſome port of England, where they might moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſlie helpe themſelues. Wherevpon it was carried to Waymouth the next day following. For al the miſhap that befell this ſhip, they vnderſtood that the Spaniards had taken out of her al the beſt things that they could, caſting off the bulke of her togither with certaine groſſe ſtuffe therein, as for that time altogither vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>About this time her Maieſtie ſéeing that all hope of peace was fruſtrate, called home againe her Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners from Flanders, who were by the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> moſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2799:11"/> diſmiſſed, very honorablie accompanied, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their cariages ſafe conducted to the marches of Calis, which way they tooke their iourney.</p>
            <p>But to the matter: the night laſt before mentioned there befell a great calme, and therevpon <hi>4.</hi> Spaniſh Galliaſſes ſeuered themſelues from the reſt of their fléete. This thing made the Engliſhmen to doubt that that night they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to giue the onſet vpon ſome of their leſſer ſhips, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that they might annoy them the rather for that they were the rereward of the fléete. But afterwards the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſſes (whatſoeuer the occaſion was) enterpriſed nothing, either for that they ſaw they could not ſafely do it, or elſe bicauſe their mindes were not throughly ſetled vpon that which before they thought to do: a thing many times fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out in ſuch perſons as are but poore in counſell and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that they continue in their perplexed conceites without any effect or commoditie enſuing thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As appeereth in the 5. table.</note>The morning following being Tueſday the <hi>23.</hi> of the moneth, the wind was at North Eaſt, wherupon the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards came backe vpon the Engliſhmen with the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the wind, directing their courſe toward the land: the which courſe was not profitable for the Engliſhmen. Therefore to take the aduantage of the Enemie, they caſt about toward the weſt with a reaſonable compaſſe, their ſhips being very good both of ſaile and ſtirrage, that they might bring about their purpoſe. Now the Spaniards to hinder their intent,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 5. table.</note> after they perceiued it, offered to come néere aboord to fight with them, truſting in the huge great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and height of their ſhips. The which offer of theirs the Engliſh men refuſed not, but began preſently to bring themſelues into battell aray, which the enimie perceiuing he alſo did the like.</p>
            <p>In this caſe the Arke, the Lyon, the Beare, the Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Ionas, the Victorie and certaine other ſhips were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to follow the ſhip called the <hi>Non Pariglin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean ſeaſon the Triumphe with other <hi>5.</hi> ſhips
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2799:11"/> of London, namely the Merchant Roiall, the Centurion, the Margerie Ioan, the Marie Roſe, and the Golden Lion were ſo far to the rereward, and ſo far ſeuered from the reſt of the fleete, that the Galliaſſes vndertooke to giue them an hard aſſault. But they were well intertained by the ſhips for the ſpace of an hower and an halfe, vntill at the length ſome of the Quéenes ſhips, comming to ſuccor the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph and the Londoners, dealt ſo well in the matter, that the Galliaſſes were driuen to retire. The wind came about at this preſent to the South eaſt, and afterwards to the South weſt and by ſouth, at which time a certaine number or Squadron of the Quéenes together with other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhips gaue aſſault vnto the Spaniſh fléete,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 6. table.</note> and that ſo furiouſly to the weſtward of them, that the Spaniards were all enforced to giue them waie: For which cauſe the Lord Admirall conſidering both the diſcommoditie and danger, whereinto the Triumph and the other fiue ſhips were come, he called other of the Quéenes ſhips that were not far off, and gaue them ſtreight commandement to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, and to charge the enimies which were to the weſt ward with all their force: giuing further order to them all, not to diſcharge any one péece of ordinance before they ſhould come within a muſket ſhot of the enemy, in as much as that was the onely way to ſuccour the ſhips of their friends with the greater damage of the enemie. This was well performed by the Arke, the Elizabeth Ionas,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 6. table.</note> the Galeon Leiceſter, the Golden Lyon, the Victorie, the Marie Roſe, the Dread-nought, and the Swallow. Which thing the duke of Medina perceiuing, he alſo came foorth with <hi>16.</hi> of his beſt Galeons, to hinder and impeach the Engliſhmen in the defence of the Triumph, ſéeming in this caſe to pretend, that the reaſon of the fight did ſo require; whereas the regard of his honor did no leſſe inforce him vnto it: bicauſe it ſéemed vnconuenient that he ſhould in euery thing be inferior to the Engliſhmen: and therefore he made large promiſes vnto thoſe by whoſe meanes the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2799:12"/> victorie ſhould be gotten. Howbeit that fell out in the ende that was prefixed by the ſtarres, that is, that the ſucceſſe of the conflict falling out on his ſide as hardlie as in ſuch a caſe might be, the Spaniards in the ende were enforced to giue place and to retire vnto their array of battell. In this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict one <hi>William Cocks</hi> captaine of a little pinneſſe called the Violet, belonging vnto ſir <hi>William Winter,</hi> behaued himſelfe very valiantly againſt the enemie in the greateſt heate of this incounter: but within a little while after, he loſt his delight wherewith he was not very well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his life by a great péece of ordinance, fortune not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing correſpondently fauorable vnto his courage, which therefore was not whit profitable to the perfection of his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As appeereth in the 6. table.</note>Toward the euening <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5.</hi> Spaniſh ſhips came out from the reſt of the fleete from the ſouth eaſtward, againſt whom certaine of the Engliſh ſhips came, and namely the Maie flower of London, which diſcharged certaine pieces vpon the enemie with a very honorable declaration of the Marine diſcipline, and being accompanied by other ſhips that were there found they all behaued themſelues no leſſe diligently (which thing was not at the firſt hoped for) ſhewing their deſire tempered with a wiſh of other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie. The conflict continued from the morning vnto the euening, the L. Admirall being at all times ready and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant in all aduentures that might fal out: And thereupon he was ſometimes more, and ſometimes leſſe eger in the conflict as neceſſity required, giuing thereby euident exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple how others ſhould behaue themſelues. It might well be ſaid that for the time it was not poſſible to ſée before this battell in this ſea ſo hard a conflict, nor ſo terrible a ſpoile of ſhips, by reaſon of the pellets that flew ſo thicke euerie way: to conclude, there was neuer ſéene ſo vehement a fight, either ſide indeuoring through an headſtrong and deadly hatred the others ſpoile and deſtruction. For albeit the muſquettiers and harquebuſiers were in either fléete
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2799:12"/> many in number, yet could they not be diſcerned or heard, by reaſon of the more violent and roaring ſhot of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ordinance, that followed ſo thicke one vpon another, and plaied ſo well that day on either ſide, that they were thought to be equall in number to common harquebuſiers in an hot ſkirmiſh. The battell was not onely long, but alſo néere at hand within halfe a muſket ſhot, and that to the great aduantage of the Engliſhmen, who with their ſhips, being (as was aforeſaid) excellent of ſaile and ſtirrage, yet leſſe a great deale then the Spaniſh ſhips, and therfore more light and nimble, ſought not at all, according to their maner otherwiſe, to boord them, but kéeping themſelues aloofe at a reaſonable diſtance, continually beate vpon the hull and tacklings of their enemies ſhips, which being a great deale higher could not ſo conueniently beat the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh ſhips with their ordinance. This long conflict being finiſhed and euery one retiring vnto his part, the next daie following (which was wedneſday the <hi>24.</hi> of the moneth) was paſſed without any thing done, bicauſe by reaſon of the fight that day before there was ſpent a great quantitie of powder and ſhot: whereupon the L. Admirall ſent diuers barkes and pinneſſes to the ſhore for a new ſupplie of ſuch munition. For her Maieſtie prudently foreſéeing ech thing neceſſary for her men, ordained that there ſhould be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent prouiſion made, according as ſhould be néedfull, aſwell of victuals as of munition. It ſéemed moreouer that daie that the Spaniſh fléete was nothing gréeued with that dais reſpite, but were all of them indifferently glad of that brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, inaſmuch as thereby they had good oportunitie to looke to their leaks, wherof no doubt they had a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for they had carried away many ſhrewd ſtripes from their enimies, their hurts being of great likelihood ſo much the more in that the Spaniards were pend vp in a narrow roome.<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 6. table.</note> This day the L. Admirall for certaine conuenient reaſons, deuided the whole body of the fléete into fower ſquadrons, by meanes of which diuiſion the enimy might
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2799:13"/> be greatly and more continually troubled. The firſt ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron he kept for himſelfe: the ſecond he aſſigned vnto ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> his Vice admerall: the third to M. <hi>Iohn Hawkins:</hi> the fourth to M. <hi>Martin Frobiſher,</hi> and after noone he gaue order, that in the night fire of the merchants ſhips in ech ſquadron (for that as they were of ſundry parts of the Realme, ſo they were equally diuided into ech ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron) ſhould charge the Spaniſh fléete in as many parts at one and the ſame time, that at midnight the enimie might be kept occupied. This order taken (as it was verie likelie) might haue had as good effect as it was wiſely giuen: but by reaſon of a great calme which fell out, no part of this aduiſement could be accompliſhed, fortune interrupting good counſell.</p>
            <p>The next day being the 25. of the moneth and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his day, there was a great Spaniſh Galleon left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind her companie to the South ward néere to the ſquadron of Maſter <hi>Iohn Hawkins:</hi>
               <note place="margin">As appeereth in the 7. table.</note> ſo that the barkes belonging vnto the greater ſhips, were within Muſket ſhot of hir. By reaſon hereof 3. of the Galliaſſes and another ſhip that was in maner of a Galleon and well appointed, came from the Spaniſh fléete to ſuccor this Galleon. Againſt whom went out the L. Admirall in the Arke and the L. <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> in the golden Lion, and drew ſo néere being towed by their boats, that they did them much harme, whereby one of them requiring the helpe of the reſt, being ſuccored by them returned vnto the fléete: And from another, by means of a ſhot comming from the Arke, there was taken away her light and throwen into the Sea; the third loſt hir becke. Whereby theſe 2. ſhips the Arke and the golden Lion declared this day to each fléete, that they had moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and faithfull Gimners, deſirous aſwell of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, as of the priuate honor of their leaders the Lord Admirall and the L. <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> which went in them: which commendation might rightly be imparted with them concerning this happie euent, bicauſe the calme
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2799:13"/> was ſo great, that albeit the two fléets were well able to behold the fortune of ech of their friends, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they could not helpe them at all: at the length the winde beginning ſomewhat to ariſe, the Spaniards tooke the opportunitie thereof, and put themſelues foreward to helpe thoſe of their ſide, and ſuccoured them honorablie. After this time the Galliaſſes in whoſe puiſſance the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt hope of the Spaniſh fléete was founded, were neuer ſéene to fight anymore, ſuch was their interteinment that daie.</p>
            <p>The two fléetes notwithſtanding approching nigh one vnto another began a conflict, but they continued it but a while, except one ſhip called the Non Pariglia, &amp; another called the Marie Roſe, which hauing taken in their top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes ſtaied themſelues there, to make as it were a certain experience of their manhood vpon the Spaniſh fléete, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing themſelues honorably for a ſeaſon. In which time, the Triumph being to the northward of the Spaniſh fléet, was ſo far off, that doubting that certaine of the Spaniſh ſhips would aſſault her to the windeward, they ſuccoured her with diuers boates that got the winde eaſilie: for the Beare and the Elizabeth Ionas euen at one inſtant ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge of the danger wherein the other were, drew néere vnto them,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 7. table.</note> deſiring both in regard of the honor of their common-wealth, and alſo for the preſeruation of their friends and countrymen, to be partakers of the like danger and difficultie.</p>
            <p>Whereupon ech ſhip doing her dutie they iointly ſaued the Triumph from all harme, and recouered the winde. And thus this daies worke ended: whereof I may ſay, that the conflict was no whit ſhorter then the day it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>At this preſent the Engliſhmen conſidering the great waſt of powder and ſhot that had heretofore béen made, the L. Admirall determined not to aſſault the enemie any more, vntill he were come nigh vnto Douer, in which place he knew he ſhould find the fléete vnder the charge of the L.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2799:14"/> 
               <hi>Seymer,</hi> and ſir <hi>William Winter,</hi> who were ready to ioine with him, that thereby he might both fortifie himſelfe with a greater number of ſhips, and in this maner prouide them ſelues of munition from that part of the Realme. Vpon friday therefore being the <hi>26.</hi> of the moneth ceaſing from fighting, the L. Admirall (aſwell for their good deſerts and honorable ſeruice, as alſo to encourage others to like valor) was deſirous to aduance certaine perſonages to the degrée of knighthood, for that behauing themſelues manfully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well with their ſhips as their good aduiſe, they were woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie that degree of honor: and ſo much the more woorthie in that being farre ſeparated from all courtly fauour, which many times imparteth the chéefeſt honors vnto the leaſt deſeruing men,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 8. table.</note> they declared their valor in the eies of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fléete.</p>
            <p>Therfore the two Lords, viz. the L. <hi>Howard,</hi> and the L. <hi>Sheffeild: Roger Townſend, Iohn Hawkins</hi> and <hi>Martin Frobiſher</hi> were called foorth, and the order of knighthoode giuen them by the L. Admirall as their generall.</p>
            <p>This day there came to the ſeruice of her Maieſtie in her fléete diuers Gentlemen, honorable both by blood and place, but much more in reſpect of their courage and vertue, for that in theſe publike affaires and ſo neceſſary ſeruice of the wars, they willingly offred their ſeruice in the defence of their countrey and honor of her maieſtie.</p>
            <p>This day alſo and the next being the <hi>27.</hi> the Spaniards followed their courſe quietly before the Engliſh fléete. In which time the E. of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> the L. <hi>Buckhurſt,</hi> ſir <hi>George Carie</hi> knight, and the captaines of the fortes and caſtels thereabout, ſent their men with powder, ſhot and victuals, to the L. Admirall to aſſiſt and helpe the armie. The ſame Satturday towards the euening the Spaniards drew nigh to Calis vnder the coaſt of Picardie,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 9. table.</note> and there ſodenly caſt anker almoſt right againſt the left hand of the hauen to the weſtward, a little leſſe then fiue miles from Calis cléeues. The Engliſh fléete alſo caſt anker within a culuerin ſhot of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2799:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the enemie to the weſtward.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon the L. <hi>Seymer</hi> and ſir <hi>William Winter</hi> ioined with the L. Admirall, wherby the Engliſh fléete increaſed to the number of 140. ſhips of all ſorts. But the Spaniards with all ſpéede ſent tidings vnto the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> of their arriuall, who at this preſent was at Bruges, who hauing retained with him all his ſeafaring men many daies before to this purpoſe, yet procéeded no farther in the matter for that time, although for ſuch time as the king had limited him, he for his part tooke as much care as might be looked for at his hands. For hauing alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die imbarked a certaine number of his ſoldiors, he was carefull in like maner to diſpatch the reſt as ſoone as they ſhould be ready, that they might take oportunitie to come foorth, furniſhing them abundantly with victuall and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. But in the meane time ſuch a chance fell out as made fruſtrate not onely his, but the conceite alſo of the duke of Medina, and wholie ouerthrew their enterpriſe, in that her Maieſtie was not a little carefull and troubled in minde concerning the ſucceſſe of theſe affaires, albeit ſhe herſelfe had committed her whole fortune into the hands of almightie God.</p>
            <p>Moreouer alſo the L. Admirall hauing by certaine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice vnderſtoode, that the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> had prepared a great number of tunnes of water, and ten thouſand choſen footemen to be embarked for the ioyning with the fléete, which could not be auoided if the duke of Medina were not compelled to auoide that place, knowing alſo the euident perill that was to be feared, if the Spaniſh fléete ſhould be ſuffered to refreſh it ſelfe, and to be furniſhed with ſo many ſoldiors, he applied his wits ſo in the deliberation of theſe matters of waight and importance, hauing the conſent of others more practiſed, that no time might be loſt for the furtherance of this ſeruice: and for ſo much as the forces of the enimie were not yet vnited and ioined togither, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>28.</hi> of this moneth at midnight he prouided eight
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2799:15"/> ſmall ſhips dreſſed with artificial fire, to the intent to driue the ſame vpon the Spaniſh fléete.<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 9. table.</note> This thing was dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and effectually brought to paſſe vnder the charge of captaine <hi>Yoong</hi> and captaine <hi>Prewſe,</hi> two valiant and couragious men. By reaſon hereof the enimie was not onely enforced to breake his ſléepe, but the fire comming ſo ſodenly vpon him (not remembring himſelfe at the verie inſtant time of any other remedy, either more ſafe for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or more excuſable) to cut his cables, to let ſlip his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and to hoyſe vp ſailes as the onely way to ſaue his fléete from ſo imminent and vnexpected a miſchiefe. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore by meanes of this tumult and confuſion (which in truth was very great) the chéefe Galliaſſe fell foule with another ſhip, vpon the cable of whoſe anker her ſterne was ſet ſo faſt, that they could not looſe her al the night long, ſo that the next day following ſhe was enforced with her oares to make toward the land, and to draw nigh to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens mouth of Calis, to ſaue hirſelfe in that place: but not knowing that water, and hauing no profitable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient counſell for the time, ſhe fell vpon a ſhelfe. This thing being in good time eſpied by the L. Admirall,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 10. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> he ſent thither his greateſt boate vnder the charge of <hi>Amieus Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> his lieutenant, and togither with him <hi>Thomas Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> and M. <hi>Haruie</hi> two of her maieſties Gentlemen and ſeruants, and others of the court, and of his own ſeruants, who fought with her, but vnequally, for that the ſhip being graueled could with her force preuaile but little. In this conflict it chanced that a muſket ſhot ſtroke <hi>Hugo de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cada</hi> chéefe captaine of the Galliaſſe, a noble and valiant man, in the head. The which miſhap ioined with the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of ſtirring themſelues in their defence, bred ſuch a deſpaire in euery man, that the greater ſort lept into the water to ſaue themſelues by ſwimming into the hauen, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many of them periſhed in the water. By this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of the enimy, the Engliſhmen being more ſecure, tooke her and ſacked her to their great commoditie, aboue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2799:15"/> an hundred men being entred into her, and their company increaſing more and more.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon <hi>Monſieur Gordon</hi> gouernor of Calis, a man of good eſtimation in reſpect of his prerogatiue in that place, ſent his nephew to giue the Engliſhmen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that they ſhould content themſelues with the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpoile, and that they ſhould leaue behind them the great ordinance, as a thing belonging vnto him by vertue of his office. The which embaſſage ſent the ſecond time vnto men more intentiue vnto their pray then other mens rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, made the Gentleman to be euilly intertained by our men, in ſuch ſort, that they would haue forceably taken from him ſome trifeling things about him, thinking him to be a Spaniard. Wherat <hi>M. Gordon</hi> being offended, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed certaine péeces of ordinance to be diſcharged from the Towne, and then the Engliſhmen departed, leauing the Galliaſſe at his pleaſure after the loſſe of ſome ſoldiors, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing notwithſtanding ſacked <hi>22000.</hi> duckets of gold, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining vnto the king, and <hi>14.</hi> coffers of mooueables of the duke of Medina, with ſome other both money and mooueables of other particular men, and ſome priſoners, among whom was <hi>Don Roderigo</hi> of Mendoza, and <hi>Don Iohn Gonzales de Solerzauo</hi> vnder captaine of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſſe.</p>
            <p>During the time of ſurpriſing of which Galliaſſe, ſir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> Vice admirall being in the ſhip called the Reuenge,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 10. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> accompanied with <hi>Tho. Fenner</hi> captaine of the Non Pariglia, with the reſt of that ſquadron, ſet vpon the Spaniſh fléete, giuing them an hot charge. Within a while after ſir <hi>Iohn Hawkins</hi> in the Victorie accompanied with <hi>Edward Fenton</hi> captain of the Marie Roſe, with <hi>George Beeſton</hi> captain in the Dread-nought, and <hi>Richard Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> in the Swallow, with the reſt of that ſquadron, put themſelues foreward and brake through the midſt of the Spaniſh fléete, where there began a vehement conflict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing all the morning, wherein euery captaine did verie
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2799:16"/> honorable ſeruice: among the reſt captain <hi>Beeſton</hi> deſerued ſpecial praiſe. Vnto this fight came the L. Admirall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the Earle of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> thei L. <hi>Thomas Howard,</hi> the L. <hi>Sheffeilde,</hi> and in that place where the fight was made, and the victory was gotten, they were publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commended, that of their owne accord had made ſhewe of the fruits anſwerable to the hope before conceiued of them. Not far from this place there was a great Spaniſh galeon ſéen, which was ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the one ſide by the Earle of <hi>Cumberland</hi> and <hi>George Ryman</hi> in the Bonaduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and on the otherſide by the L. <hi>Seymer,</hi> in the ſhip cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Raynbowe, and ſir <hi>William Winter</hi> in the Vant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, yet ſhe ſaued her ſelfe valiantly, gathering into the body of the fléete,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 10. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> although with ill ſucceſſe: for ſhe was ſo beaten and ſo terribly rent and torne with our great ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that the night following in the ſight of her owne fléete, ſhe ſunke, her men, as is thought, being ſaued. After this captaine <hi>Fenton</hi> in the Marie Roſe, and a Spaniſh Galeon met togither, being eaſt and weſt one of another, yet no nigher then that their ſhot might plaie ſafelie, and flie betwéen them without any great hurt. Captaine <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> notwithſtanding and thoſe that were with him, were woorthilie commended for their ſeruice begun and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with ſuch proſperous boldnes. The ſame day the déedes of ſir <hi>Robert Southwell</hi> were euidently ſéene: for being a man borne to vertue and commendation, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to purchaſe honor, to the end that he might not make fruſtrate the iudgement of his Soueraigne, who before time had made him knight, diuining how much in time to come he would further the profite of the common wealth of England, he enforced himſelfe not onely to ſatiſfie either in counſel or paines the publike intent, but alſo the priuate commoditie of the L. Admirall his Father in lawe, in that he had dutifully promiſed him ſure and faithfull ſeruice, whereupon for the ſame he receiued condigne praiſe of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man. Ther was alſo particularly praiſed <hi>Robert Croſſe</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2799:16"/> captaine, who in the ſhip called the Hope, gaue a ſigne of fruite to be looked for in him, not inferior vnto that which the ſhip wherein he went did by the name it caried, cauſe vs to hope for.</p>
            <p>It fell out alſo the ſame day, that the L. <hi>Henrie Seimer</hi> and ſir <hi>William Winter</hi> did ſo throughly beate two Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Galeons, although they were of the chéefeſt of them and the beſt prouided, that they were inforced to withdraw themſelues to the coaſt of Flanders, where forſomuch as they were in a very euill taking, as well in reſpect of the murther of their men, as the manifolde leakes of their ſhips, they were ſurpriſed, and without fight rifeled by the Zelanders, and with all the men in them caried as priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto Fluſhing. Among theſe, the chéefeſt was <hi>Don Diego Pimentello,</hi> a man very famous among his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey people.</p>
            <p>It ſéemeth héerby that we may with reaſon gather, that in theſe conflicts many of the Spaniſh ſhips periſhed, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it that moſt men thinke that few of them miſcaried. After this battell which was made the 29. of the moneth, the L. Admirall the <hi>30.</hi> day ordained, that the L. <hi>Seimer</hi> and ſir <hi>W. Winter</hi> ſhould returne with their fléete vnto their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed office in the chanell, which was to kéepe the coaſt from the danger that the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> ſéemed to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. The which duke had already loſt the opportunitie of being able to do any thing for the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhing of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intention of the Spaniards, or according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions receiued from the Spaniſh king whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they were: Bicauſe the ſudden and vnlooked for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the duke of <hi>Medina</hi> with the whole fléete from the coaſt of Calice, and his ſmall aboade vpon any other coaſt, cauſed the whole care of the aforeſaid duke that he tooke vpon the maine land, to become voide, ſo that he did not imbarke the reſt of his men to ioine with the duke of <hi>Medina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Admirall therefore determined to follow the<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 11. tabl.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2799:17"/> Spaniſh fléete onely ſo long vntill they might be ſhot vp to the Northward, whither the Spaniſh fléete directed hir courſe, but to what end it was not knowen. And that he with the ſame winde might come to the Fyrth, which is vpon the coaſt of Scotland, if ſo be that he ſaw the enimie paſſe thoſe parts. Whereupon he thought moreouer, that it was good to ſtay his fléete from attempting ought vpon the Spaniard, vntill he ſhould haue good intelligence of their purpoſe, thereby to worke a meane vtterly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe and otherthrow them. But the Spaniards kept their courſe about the Ilands of Orknay, declaring thereby, that they minded to returne that way into Spaine along by the North coaſt of Scotland, which as ſkilfull men coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, would be to their euident danger, as it fell out after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 11. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> Perceiuing therefore the purpoſe of the enimie, when he was ſhot vp <hi>55.</hi> deg. <hi>13.</hi> min. to the Northward, and 30. leagues of from Newcaſtell, the L. Admirall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued with himſelfe to let the Spaniſh fléete kéepe on hir way: Albeit at the firſt he was minded to giue them a ſtrong aſſault vpon the ſecond of Auguſt: but perſuaded otherwiſe by a more ſafe aduiſe and counſell, he wiſely ſtaied himſelfe from that action, leauing the euent that ſhould inſue vnto fortune, who might worke ſome farther matter vpon them: ſéeing the enimie had taken that way to ſaue himſelfe. Moreouer, he conſidered the ſcarcitie of munition, wherof at that preſent he had but litle, and that vpon this occaſion, for that the ſhips that lay on the coaſt appointed by order from hir Maieſtie to carrie ſuch proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, knew not where to finde our fléete in time conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</p>
            <p>The Spaniſh fléete therefore, as for hir owne welfare it was requiſite, hauing gon on ſo far before, the L. Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſolued to put into the Fyrth in Scotland, as well to refreſh himſelfe with new victuals, as alſo to diſpatch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other matters which he thought neceſſarie. But the winde being much weſtward and againſt him, the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2799:17"/> he changed his courſe, and returned into England with his whole fléete the 7. of Auguſt, although by reaſon of a tempeſt which befell them, part of the ſhips put into Douer, part to Harwich, the reſt into Yarmouth.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I haue deſcribed, according to the inſtructions and direction which I receiued of thoſe things that fell out betwéene the Engliſhmen and the Spaniards, adioining thereunto ſuch particular diſcourſes as I thought to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, and ſuch ornaments of ſpéech as the matter and the Italian toong did ſpecially require: Now therefore it remaineth for the finiſhing of our former diſcourſe, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and euidently to ſet downe the iſſue of all the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
            <p>THe Spaniſh fléete paſſing (as aforeſaid) into thoſe ſeas, which for the moſt part are quiet and calme inough, whether it were driuen too and fro in them with contrarie winds, or by ſome other fatall accident that fell out, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued therein toſſed vp and downe vntill the ende of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,<note place="margin">As appeereth in the 11. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> with fearefull ſucceſſe and deadlie ſhipwracke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the whole coaſt of Ireland: ſo that the duke of <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Sidonia</hi> was enforced to leaue there behind him about the number of <hi>17.</hi> good ſhips, beſides thoſe <hi>15.</hi> that were thought to be loſt in the monethes of Iulie and Auguſt, and ſo to returne into Spaine.</p>
            <p>The perſons loſt in Ireland were eſtéemed to be about <hi>5500.</hi> So that all being accounted togither, it is certainlie auouched, that al the ſhips that were loſt amount vnto the number of <hi>32.</hi> and the men accounted one with another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to the number of <hi>13500.</hi> or more. The priſoners alſo of all ſorts in England, Ireland, &amp; the low Countries ariſe to the number of <hi>2000.</hi> and more. As for the loſſe of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante, &amp; the common or priuate treaſure, or whether the duke after he was preſerued from the former fearefull and mortall dangers loſt any more ſhips, or no, or laſt of all, how many he brought home with him againe into Spain,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2799:18"/> I meane not to occupie or trouble my pen with any ſuch ſuperfluous curioſities, being willing to leaue that matter vnto ſuch as haue receiued certaine tidings therof: bicauſe I ſtudie (ſo farre foorth as is poſſible) for breuitie without procuring vnto any man either hatred or euill report.</p>
            <p>And therefore to knit vp this preſent treatiſe, this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that after her Maieſtie was throughly aſſured of the returne of the duke into Spain, and that her ſeas were cléere and free from al her enimies, and hauing called home the L. <hi>Seymer</hi> with his fleete, it ſeemed good vnto her (as a conuenient thing) that her people ſhould render vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God as great thanks as might be, for that it had pleaſed him thus to work and bring about the deliuerance of them all. And therefore the 19. of Nouember, by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like edict and order from her Maieſtie, there was general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made throughout the whole Realme, a moſt frequent aſſemblie of all ſorts of people publikely to giue thanks vnto God all the day long, for ſo ſingular a benefit recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, with this intention, that the remembrance of the ſaid benefit, ſhould vpon the ſame day of euery yéere to enſue, be renued in the minde and eies of all men throughout the whole nation, with an euident and religious acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the common ſafetie of them all was accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the ſpeciall fauor of God, the Father of all good things.</p>
            <p>Her Maieſtie alſo being afterwards deſirous to do the like in her owne behalfe (as it was conuenient) came into Paules Church in London on Sonday being the 24. of the ſame moneth, with a moſt decent order and aſſemblies of al the Magiſtrates and companies of the Citie ſtanding in a ranke in the ſtréet, repleniſhed moſt abundantly with people, through which her Maieſtie was to paſſe, being accompanied with ſuch a princely traine of all thoſe that had béene inſtruments of that notable victorie, that it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her Maieſtie togither with the reſt, hauing gotten the victorie, was deſirous in triumphing maner to ſhew her
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2799:18"/> thankfull minde vnto the Londoners alſo, for the charges and paines they had vndertaken all the yéere before, in the ſeruice of the Crowne and the common-wealth, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the increaſe of their owne reputation, being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the foundation and cheefe ſtaie of all the other parts of the Realme. Wherein her Maieſtie followed the example of diuers kings her predeceſſors, who vpon ſpecial fauor, according as good occaſions mooued them thereunto, haue giuen many large priuiledges and liberties vnto the ſaid Citie, which at this day is doubtleſſe more popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, more wealthie, more mightie, and more frée, then euer it was héretofore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London, by A. Hatfield, and are to be ſold at the ſhop of A. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being a little from Leaden</hi> hall next to the Signe <hi>of the Tower.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
